A Finding Aid to the Lillian and Frederick Kiesler Papers, circa 1910s-2003, bulk 1958-2000, in the Archives of American Art AAA.kieslill
Archives of American Art
Lillian and Frederick Kiesler papers
bulk 1958-2000
circa 1910s-2003
AAA.kieslill
Archives of American Art
48.2 Linear feet
The papers of New York artist Lillian Kiesler and architect and sculptor Frederick Kiesler measure 48.2 linear feet and date from circa 1910s-2003, with the bulk of the material from 1958-2000. The collection documents their personal and professional lives and the legacy of Frederick Kiesler's work through biographical material, correspondence, legal, financial and business records, teaching files, exhibition and performance files, artwork, subject files, printed material, writings and interviews, monographs, photographic material, and sound and video recordings. Also found are papers related to Abstract Expressionist painter Hans Hofmann and the papers of artist Alice Hodges.
Kiesler, Lillian
Provenance
The collection was donated by Lillian Kiesler and Maryette Charlton, executrix of her estate, in several accessions between 1980-2002. Some of the papers related to Frederick Kiesler were originally loaned for microfilming in 1971, most of which was later donated in 1980. Additional papers related to Frederick Kiesler were donated in 1993. Papers related to Hans Hofmann were given in 1981. Lillian Kiesler's papers were donated in 2000 by Lillian Kiesler, and in 2002, by Maryette Charlton.
Separated Material
Some of the materials related to Frederick Kiesler were initially loaned for microfilming on reels 57 and 127-128. This material is not described in the container listing of this finding aid. Most, but not all, of the loaned material was later donated and has been merged with the other accretions.
Related Material
The holdings of the Archives of American Art include the Hans Hofmann Papers, 1904-1978 and the Maryette Charlton Papers, 1929-1998. Additional Frederick Kiesler papers are available at the Museum of Modern Art, the Harvard Theater Collection, and the Yale School of Art and Architecture.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Frederick Kiesler (1890-1965) was a sculptor, architect, set designer, educator, and writer active in New York and Connecticutt. Lillian Kiesler (1911-2001) was a performer, arts educator, and painter married to Frederick Kiesler. She was also active in the administration of the Hans Hofmann School of Fine Arts.
Frederick Kiesler was born in Romania in 1890, although he gave various other dates for his birth and regularly cited Vienna as his birthplace. He arrived in the United States with his wife Steffi in 1926 for the International Theatre Exposition at Steinway Hall in New York City. They stayed in the United States and were granted citizenship in 1936.
Kiesler secured a teaching position at Columbia University's School of Architecture in 1930, and from 1934 through 1957 he was the scenic design director at The Juilliard School of Music. He also lectured at Yale University from 1950-1952. Often labeled a Surrealist, Kiesler's work was experimental and frequently described as ahead of its time. He published, lectured, and participated in numerous exhibitions throughout his career. He is known for his theory of "coreallism;" "The Space House" (1933), a full-scale model of a single family home; an installation designed for Peggy Guggenheim's Art of This Century gallery in 1942; "The Endless House" drawings and model (1950); "The Universal Theatre" (1961) model; and the Shrine of the Book (1965), a building to exhibit the Dead Sea Scrolls in Jerusalem. He died in New York City in December 1965.
Lillian Olinsey met architect and sculptor Frederick Kiesler in 1934. After years of friendship, they were married in 1964, a year and a half before Frederick's death in 1965.
Lillian Kiesler studied art at the Art Students League, Cooper Union, and the Hans Hofmann School of Fine Arts, where she also assisted Hofmann and the school administration. She taught art to children and young adults for twenty years in New York City. From 1945 to 1955, she taught at the Greenwich House Art workshops and the Woodward School, followed by the Brooklyn Museum (1948-1958), Barnard School (1953-1963), New York University School of Education (1955-1966), and Juilliard School of Visual Arts (1963-1965). Lillian was involved in the performing arts and between the late 1970s through the 1990s she performed in New York City with numerous directors, notably Jo Andres, Steve Buscemi, Richard Foreman, John Jesurun, Cindy Lubar, and Tim Miller. She frequently performed with her close friend, painter Maryette Charlton, who was the executor of the Lillian Kiesler estate.
Lillian Kiesler tirelessly promoted Frederick Kiesler's work and legacy after his death in 1965. From the late 1980s through the 1990s, she delivered lectures about his work at universities and museums, gave interviews, corresponded with researchers, and organized his papers to donate to the Harvard Theatre Collection, Yale School of Art and Architecture, and the Archives of American Art. In 1997, she helped found the Frederick and Lillian Kiesler Foundation in Vienna, Austria. She endowed the Austrian Frederick Kiesler Prize, an award given to a notable contributor to the field of architecture. The first recipient was Frank Gehry in 1998. Lillian Kiesler passed away in 2001 in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of artist, performer, and arts educator Lillian Kiesler and sculptor, architect, set designer, educator, and writer Frederick Kiesler measure 48.2 linear feet and date from circa 1910s-2003, with the bulk of the material from 1958-2000. The collection documents their personal and professional lives and the legacy of Frederick Kiesler's work through biographical material, correspondence, legal, financial and business records, teaching files, exhibition and performance files, artwork, subject files, printed material, writings and interviews, monographs, photographic material, and sound and video recordings. Also found are papers related to Abstract Expressionist painter Hans Hofmann and the papers of artist Alice Hodges.
The collection is arranged into two series: the Lillian Kiesler Papers (Series 1) and the Frederick Kiesler Papers (Series 2). Measuring 41.1 linear feet, the Lillian Kiesler Papers (Series 1) make up the bulk of the collection and document her personal life and professional career as an artist, actor, teacher, arts benefactor and promoter of Frederick Kiesler's legacy. The series spans her lifetime, although most of the material is dated after 1965. Among her papers are biographical materials, correspondence, legal and financial records, teaching files, exhibition and performance files, artwork, subject files, printed material, monographs, papers related to Frederick Kiesler and his legacy, papers of and related to Hans Hofmann, papers of Alice Hodges, photographic material, and sound and video recordings.
Found among Lillian Kiesler's personal papers are address books, numerous calendars and appointment books, and diaries and journals. Her correspondence is extensive and contains business correspondence with John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, The Whitney Museum of American Art, The University of Iowa Museum of Art, and Erick Hawkins Dance Foundation, and personal letters and greeting cards from friends, family, artists, scholars, and researchers, including Etel Adnan, Alcopley, Fritz Bultman, Steve Buscemi, Mike Diamond, Burgoyne Diller, Lucia Dlugoszewski, Piero Dorazio, Jean Dubuffet, Jay Gottlieb, Erick Hawkins, Burgess Meredith, Henry Miller, James Purdy, and Herrel Thomas. Of interest is a letter from Harry Holtzman postmarked March 13, 1935 describing his initial meeting with Mondrian, and a letter from E.B. Gordon describing Henry Miller in Paris.
Materials related to Lillian Kiesler's estate and last wishes can also be found, as well as teaching plans, student work, and writings by Lillian Kiesler's mentor and friend, New York University professor Chandler Montgomery. Various printed material, correspondence, scripts, and rehearsal schedules from Lillian Kiesler's exhibitions and performances are also found, and among the directors, artists and writers represented are Jo Andres, Steve Buscemi, Cindy Lugar, Tim Miller and James Purdy. Artwork contains photographs by Bob Del Fredici, drawings by Piero Dorazio, and notes to Frederick Kiesler from Lillian Kiesler.
Subject files about artists, friends, colleagues, performances, and organizations in which she supported, such as the Anthology Film Archives, include printed materials and research materials. Signed exhibition catalogs of Loren MacIver, Dina Ghen, Lenore Tawney, and Toshiko Takaezu, and a reprint article inscribed by Alcopley can be found, as well as numerous inscribed monographs, including books inscribed by Max Weiler and Piero Dorazio, an inscribed first edition of Henry Miller's Black Spring (1936), and a 1937 monograph by Harry Holtzman titled American Abstract Artists.
Series 1 also includes materials related to her husband Frederick Kiesler, papers of and related to Abstract Expressionist painter Hans Hofmann, and the personal papers of artist Alice Hodges. The Papers Related to Frederick Kiesler were primarily created or compiled by Lillian Kiesler and document her work on behalf of Frederick Kiesler's legacy. Of interest are letters from Frederick Kiesler to Lillian Kiesler and Alice Hodges; a bound volume of correspondence to Piero Dorazio; an inventory of objects in the Frederick Kiesler estate; photographs of artwork; an interview (sound recordings and transcript) with Lillian Kiesler about Frederick Kiesler for "Music of the Age," included on the tape is a portion of a Frederick Kiesler interview (1965); a recording of Lillian Kiesler interviewing Richard Kamler about Frederick Kiesler; and Frederick Kiesler's dialogue with Leo Castelli (undated).
Lillian Kiesler was a student of Hans Hofmann (1880-1966) in New York City and Provincetown, Massachusetts, as well as an enthusiastic volunteer promoter and assistant to The Hans Hofmann School of Fine Arts. The bulk of the papers of and related to Hans Hofmann were created or compiled by Lillian Kielser and are about Hofmann's career and legacy. However, also found are some papers of Hans Hofmann, including letters from Hofmann to Lillian Kiesler and Alice Hodges describing his artwork, life in Provincetown, and issues with The Hans Hofmann School of Fine Arts, typed and handwritten lectures given by Hofmann, Hofmann's 1941 address to the American Abstract Artists (AAA), three boxes of card files on students of the Hans Hofmann School of Fine Arts in New York City and Provincetown, and photographs of Hofmann and his house in Provincetown taken by Wilfrid Zogbaum and Tom Milius.
The artist Alice Hodges (b. unknown-1965) was a close friend of Lillian Kiesler, a former secretary to Frederick Kiesler, and a student of Hans Hofmann. Included among her personal papers is some correspondence from Hans Hofmann and Katherine Drier and numerous postcards from Hodges and Lillian Kiesler's trip to Europe in 1950, posters and printed material from her exhibitions, an oversized scrapbook chronicling Lillian Kiesler's teaching career, records from the United States Treasury War Bond Art Auction in 1945, original artwork and greeting cards made by Hodges and Lillian Kiesler, and 31 rolled negative strips in metal canisters of Frederick Kiesler sculptures, Provincetown and Hans Hofmann, Wellfleet, Empire State Music Festival (1955), and travels to Colorado and Europe, some of which may be printed and found in this subseries.
Photographs found in the Lillian Kiesler Papers are mostly black and white and color snapshots of Lillian Kiesler's friends and family at events and at home, including candid photos of Hans Hofmann, Alice Hodges, Frederick Kiesler, and Alcopley. Slides prepared by Lillian Kiesler for a lecture on Frederick Kiesler and her lecture notes on index cards are found. Sound and video recordings include recordings of productions in which Lillian Kiesler performed, and music, film, or live stage performances written, directed, or performed by friends.
Measuring 7.1 linear feet, Frederick Kiesler's personal papers (Series 2) document his professional career and date from 1923-1992. Biographical materials include his curriculum vitae, four passports, and numerous appointment books and notes from late in his life. Correspondence with architects, publishers, editors, universities, museums, galleries, manufacturers, artists and friends includes letters from L. Alcopley, Leopold Arnaud, Armand P. Bartos, Piero and Virginia Dorazio, George Howe, Kay Johnson, Jane Owen, and others. There are also photocopied letters from Katherine Dreier, Marcel Duchamp, and Piet Mondrian. Business and financial records from the 1940s to mid-1960s comprise a significant bulk of this series and are primarily tax returns and receipts and statements used to file tax returns. Materials on the publication of "Inside the Endless House" (1966), the International Theatre Exposition (in German) in 1924 and other exhibits from shortly after his death are found, as well as student artwork and papers from Kiesler's classes in the mid-1950s. A bound copy of the "Bibliography of Writings of and About Frederick Kiesler" compiled by Lillian Kiesler is found, as well as printed material about Frederick Kiesler and a handful of photographs of artwork.
Users should note that Lillian Kiesler's and Frederick Kiesler's papers contain similar types of material that often overlap in subject matter, especially among the Papers Related to Frederick Kiesler (Subseries 1.10) in Series 1 and the Frederick Kiesler Papers (Series 2). This collection contains limited material related to Lillian Kiesler prior to the 1940s and Frederick Kiesler prior to his arrival in the United States in 1926.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series. Each series is divided into several subseries, with the arrangement described in detail in the series descriptions.
Series 1: Lillian Kiesler papers, circa 1910s-2003 (Box 1-39, 47-52, OV 53-55; 41.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Frederick Kiesler papers, 1923-1992 (Box 40-46, OV 53; 7.1 linear feet)
Adnan, Etel; Andres, Jo; Anthology Film Archives.; Arnaud, Leopold, 1895-; Bartos, Armand P., 1910-; Bultman, Fritz, 1919-1985; Buscemi, Steve, 1958-; Castelli, Leo; Copley, Alfred L.; Diller, Burgoyne, 1906-1965; Dlugoszewski, Lucia, 1931-2000; Dorazio, Piero, 1927-; Dorazio, Virginia Dortch; Dreier, Katherine Sophie, 1877-1952; Dubuffet, Jean, 1901-; Duchamp, Marcel, 1887-1968; Hans Hofmann School of Fine Arts; Hawkins, Erick; Hodges, Alice; Hofmann, Hans, 1880-1966; Holtzman, Harry; Howe, George, 1886-1955; John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation; Kamler, Richard; Kiesler, Frederick; Kiesler, Lillian, 1910?-2001; MacIver, Loren, 1909-; Meredith, Burgess, 1907-1997; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.).; Milius, Tom; Miller, Henry, 1891-; Mondrian, Piet, 1872-1944; Montgomery, Chandler; Owen, Jane Blaffer, 1915-2010; Purdy, James; Takaezu, Toshiko; Tawney, Lenore; University of Iowa, Museum of Art; Whitney Museum of American Art.; Zogbaum, Wilfrid, 1915-1965; Actors--New York (State)--New York; Architects--New York (State)--New York; Art patrons--New York (State)--New York; Art schools--Massachusetts--Provincetown; Art schools--New York (State)--New York; Authors--New York (State)--New York; Diaries; Educators--New York (State)--New York; Exhibition designers; Interviews; Motion pictures (visual works); Painters--New York (State)--New York; Scrapbooks; Scripts (documents); Sculptors--New York (State)--New York; Set designers--New York (State)--New York; Sound recordings; Women artists
- Lillian Kiesler papers, circa 1910s-2003; Series 1; (Box 1-39, 47-52, OV 53-55; 41.1 linear feet)
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1 documents Lillian Kiesler's personal life and professional career as an artist, actor, teacher, arts benefactor and promoter of Frederick Kiesler's legacy. Biographical material (Subseries 1.1) includes diaries, address books, calendars and appointment books, mailing lists, guest lists, identification, medical records, obituaries, and personal writings by Lillian Kiesler and others. Lillian Kiesler's correspondence (Subseries 1.2) is extensive and primarily personal in nature, including letters and greeting cards from Etel Adnan, Alcopley, Fritz Bultman, Steve Buscemi, Mike Diamond, Burgoyne Diller, Lucia Dlugoszewski, Piero Dorazio, Jean Dubuffet, Jay Gottlieb, Erick Hawkins, Burgess Meredith, Henry Miller, James Purdy, and Herrel Thomas. There is some business correspondence with museums, galleries, and foundations, including John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, The Whitney Museum of American Art, The University of Iowa Museum of Art, and Erick Hawkins Dance Foundation.
  Legal and financial files (Subseries 1.3) are related to Lillian Kiesler's estate and finances such as burial plans and her will. Teaching files (Subseries 1.4) include teaching plans and reference materials, essays, pamphlets, class lists, correspondence from schools, student artwork and essay assignments, notebooks, writings on teaching, and a book of weaving samples. Also included are writings about teaching art and lesson plans by New York University professor Chandler Montgomery.
  Exhibition and performance files (Subseries 1.5) contain correspondence, photographs, artwork, printed materials, scripts, rehearsal schedules, reviews, monographs and notes related to Kiesler's exhibitions and peformances dating from the 1970s-2001. Among the directors, artists and writers found are Jo Andres, Steve Buscemi, Cindy Lugar, Tim Miller and James Purdy. Artwork (Subseries 1.6) contains original drawings, sketches, photographs and notes by Lillian Kiesler and others, including photographs by Bob Del Fredici and drawings by Piero Dorazio. Subject files (Subseries 1.7) include collected materials about artists, friends, colleagues, performances, and organizations in which Lillian Kiesler supported, such as the Anthology Film Archives. Printed material (Subseries 1.8) includes collected postcards, magazines and magazine articles about art and performance, newspaper clippings about fellow artists, invitations and announcements, and exhibition catalogs, including several signed exhibition catalogs and a reprint article inscribed by Alcopley. Lillian Kiesler's library (Subseries 1.9) includes numerous monographs written by friends or about friends, most with inscriptions by authors. Found here are books inscribed by Max Weiler and Piero Dorazio, an inscribed first edition of Henry Miller's Black Spring (1936), and a 1937 monograph by Harry Holtzman titled American Abstract Artists.
  The Papers Related to Frederick Kiesler (Subseries 1.10) primarily were created or compiled by Lillian Kiesler and document Frederick Kiesler's legacy as an architect, sculptor, and set designer. It includes biographical material, correspondence, inventory lists, business and financial records, exhibition files, transcribed and recorded interviews, photocopied writings and notes, printed material, photographs, slides, and negatives, and sound and video recordings. This subseries is divided into ten sub-subseries, with the arrangement described in detail in the subseries description. The bulk of the Papers of and Related to Hans Hofmann (Subseries 1.11) were created or compiled by Lillian Kielser and document Hofmann's career and legacy. It includes correspondence, exhibition files, interviews and writings about Hofmann, printed materials, photographs, and sound recordings about Hans Hofmann. However, also found are papers of Hans Hofmann including some correspondence, typed and handwritten lectures given by Hofmann, literature and brochures from the Hans Hofmann School of Fine Arts and three boxes of card files on students, and photographs of Hofmann. This subseries is divided into nine sub-subseries, with the arrangement described in detail in the subseries description. The personal papers of artist Alice Hodges (Subseries 1.12) include biographical material, correspondence, exhibition files, printed material, writings, personal items, artwork, and photographs. This subseries is divided into eight sub-subseries, with the arrangement described in detail in the subseries description.
  Photographic Material (Subseries 1.13) is mostly black and white and color snapshots of Lillian Kiesler's friends and family at events and at home, including candid photos of Hans Hofmann, Alice Hodges, Frederick Kiesler, and Alcopley. Slides include those of Frederick Kiesler's work prepared by Lillian for a lecture on him and are accompanied by her notes on index cards. Sound and Video Recordings (Subseries 1.14) document productions in which Lillian Kiesler performed, and music, film, or live stage performances written, directed, or performed by friends.
  Arrangement note
  The series is arranged as 14 subseries:
  1.1: Biographical Material, 1911-2002, undated
  1.2: Correspondence, 1911-2001, undated
  1.3: Legal and Financial Records, 1938-2001, undated
  1.4: Teaching Files, 1938-1994, undated
  1.5: Exhibition and Performance Files, 1945-2002, undated
  1.6: Artwork, 1958-2001, undated
  1.7: Subject Files, 1925, 1957-2000, undated
  1.8: Printed Material, 1930-2002, undated
  1.9: Lillian Kiesler Library, 1936-2000, undated
  1.10: Papers Related to Frederick Kiesler, circa 1913-2003, undated
  1.11: Papers of and Related to Hans Hofmann, 1932-2000, undated
  1.12: Papers of Alice Hodges, circa 1910s-1965, undated
  1.13: Photographic Material, circa 1920s-2000
  1.14: Sound and Video Recordings, 1978-2001, undated
  - Biographical Material, 1911-2002, undated; 1.1
    Biographical material includes diaries, address books, calendars and appointment books, mailing lists, guest lists, identification, medical records, obituaries, and personal writings by Lillian Kiesler and others. Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Address Books, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    - Award from University of Iowa, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Oversized material housed in Box 48, Folder 1.
    - Calendars and Appointment Books, 1954-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Calendars and Appointment Books, 1980-1984, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Calendars and Appointment Books, 1990-1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1960s, 1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Diaries and Journals, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
      Includes sketches.
    - Guest Lists, 1976-2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - IDs and Cards, circa 1950s-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Keys to Bank Studio, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Oversized material housed in Box 48, Folder 2.
    - Mailing Lists and Telephone Numbers, 1993, 1999, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Medical Records, 1969, 1992-2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous Buttons, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous Personal Papers and Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Obituaries, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Readings and Astrology, 1911, 1966-1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
      See also Box 37, Folder 21 and Box 38, Folder 1.
    - Schooley's Mountain Items, 1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Writings, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Writings, 1959-2001, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Writings, Others, 1972-1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Award from University of Iowa, undated (Box 48, Folder 1)
      Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 5.